<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>software engineering on ./side_effects.sh</title>
    <link>/tags/software-engineering/</link>
    <description>Recent content in software engineering on ./side_effects.sh</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/software-engineering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Achieving fulfillment in tech</title>
      <link>/posts/fulfillment_tech/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/fulfillment_tech/</guid>
      <description>During my career as a software developer I have had many colleagues in the engineering department that had the word &amp;ldquo;senior&amp;rdquo; as part of their job title. Others used fancier alternatives such as &amp;ldquo;specialist&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;expert&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;master&amp;rdquo;. Those people were quite different among themselves in their knowledge, technical skills and attitude towards teammates to name a few. Having interacted with them for prolonged durations at a time, I realized that it is not straightforward to give a precise definition as to what makes up a &amp;ldquo;senior software engineer&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Core traits of a skilled software engineer</title>
      <link>/posts/traits_of_skilled_soft_eng/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/traits_of_skilled_soft_eng/</guid>
      <description>Making software in this day and age seems like a trivial task. There are cloud providers - Amazon Web Services (AWS), Google Cloud Platform (GCP), Azure - open-source languages, tools and frameworks, and many sources like blogs/podcasts/YouTube channels where experienced engineers share their success and failure. Thus, theoretically it should not be hard to learn a tool, write some code and solve a problem that exists in the world.
I personally agree and disagree with this statement.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software development</title>
      <link>/posts/software_development/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/software_development/</guid>
      <description>Developers, software engineers, coders. Many names that in all honesty refer to the same persona. What do these people do all day? Why are they in such high demand? Why do they get such high salaries? Why don&amp;rsquo;t they conform to the norms that people laid out for many years as far as clothing, procedures, communication skills go? I will attempt to answer these and other questions in this post.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
