<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>recap on ./side_effects.sh</title>
    <link>/tags/recap/</link>
    <description>Recent content in recap on ./side_effects.sh</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/recap/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>2020</title>
      <link>/posts/year_toughenup/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/year_toughenup/</guid>
      <description>In the last days of 2020, I cannot help but contemplate over the past year. And what a year it has been. To my family and friends I say that this was the toughest year I ever had in my lifetime. Many would agree regardless if they know me or not. Covid-19 has changed everything we know about our day-to-day. It has had repercussions on my life as well, yet I&amp;rsquo;m sure they aren&amp;rsquo;t as severe as for others.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2017</title>
      <link>/posts/year_challenges/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/year_challenges/</guid>
      <description>Today is a great day! But why is that? To answer that question first let me walk you through my year.
As is obvious I haven&amp;rsquo;t written much in 2017 and that is for a reason. I traveled, I faced obstacles and learned a lot of lessons from my mistakes. If 2016 was a year of changes then 2017 was that and some more, so I name the last 12 months - a year of challenges.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2016</title>
      <link>/posts/year_changes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/year_changes/</guid>
      <description>2016 was a rough year. Everywhere you look you see turmoil. Brexit, Trump, Syria, Nice, Berlin, Migrants, &amp;hellip; And here comes a question - has this world been in a tougher spot? Of course. And we have always persevered. How? By being human!
I will come back to this thought but first let me take you through my 2016. It was also full of highs and lows. Fortunately for me, it peaked in mainly positive outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
