<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Zax&#39; Thoughts</title>
    <link>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Zax&#39; Thoughts</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Staying present</title>
      <link>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/present_quick/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/present_quick/</guid>
      <description>If you aren&amp;rsquo;t familiar with the concept of being (in the) present, let me quickly bring you up to speed. We lead our daily lives stormed by visual stimuli. They bombard us at every step from the moment we go out into the real or the digital world. That is slowly starting to wear people down. The reason is that from an evolutionary standpoint the increased amount of visual signals make us more alert and push us in fight-or-flight mode.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goodbye cruel Facebook world I&#39;m leaving you today</title>
      <link>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/no_fb/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/no_fb/</guid>
      <description>Before I write this I want to assure you that this is no plead for attention. For anyone that has been a part of my contacts on the aforementioned social network - you would know that I am mainly reposting articles that I read. So in a sense I use FB as another way to store articles.
The other day I was talking to a friend and he said &amp;ldquo;Man, I&amp;rsquo;m gonna leave this shit one day soon&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Today is a great day ...</title>
      <link>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/challenges/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/challenges/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; already! But why is that? To answer that question first let me walk you through my year.
As is obvious I haven&amp;rsquo;t written much in 2017 and that is for a reason. I traveled, I faced obstacles and learned a lot of lessons from my mistakes. If 2016 was a year of changes then 2017 was that and some more so I name the last 12 months - a year of challenges.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2016 - A Year Of Changes</title>
      <link>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/changes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/changes/</guid>
      <description>2016 was a rough year. Everywhere you look you see turmoil. Brexit, Trump, Syria, Nice, Berlin, Migrants, &amp;hellip; And here comes a question - has this world been in a tougher spot? Of course. An we have always persevered. How? By being human!
I will come back to this thought but first let me take you through my 2016. It was also full of highs and lows. Fortunately for me it peaked in mainly positive outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Scala Christmas Tree</title>
      <link>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/xmastree/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/xmastree/</guid>
      <description>In the spirit of the Christmas and New Year&amp;rsquo;s festivities, I decided to share with you a short and fun recursive function that can warm your hearts. If not - hopefully it will warm your gray matter a bit.
import scala.annotation.tailrec def xmasTree(height: Int): Unit = { @tailrec def xmasTree(n: Int, t: Int): Unit = { if (n == t) { println(&amp;quot; &amp;quot; * (t - n) + &amp;quot;*&amp;quot; * (1 + n * 2)) println(if (n == 1) &amp;quot; # &amp;quot; else if (n == 2) &amp;quot; # &amp;quot; else List.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with nulls in Spark UDFs</title>
      <link>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/sparknulls/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/sparknulls/</guid>
      <description>Today we are discussing User Defined Functions (UDF) in Spark.
Sometimes the simplest things are hardest to work out. Let&amp;rsquo;s say I have a DataFrame created from a parquet file which can have nullable columns that are of a certain type - in this example that is Int. The reason I chose Int particularly is that it is not a trivial case i.e. it doesn&amp;rsquo;t accept nulls as values. The problem that arises is that the DataFrame can have IntegerType specified for the schema and still contain nulls.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I against I</title>
      <link>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/iagainsti/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/iagainsti/</guid>
      <description>I share with you some thoughts on a part of my life that I hold very dear to me and has kept me going through my toughest times.
I have enjoyed physical activity from a very early age. Since I was blessed with being a child of the pre-computer era I spent my free time outside on the street, playing with my peers. I clearly remember the endless summer days when I was chasing a football with my legs covered in black and blue spots from all the falls they had to bear.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trip to Rajasthan, India</title>
      <link>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/trip_rajastan/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/trip_rajastan/</guid>
      <description>I recently visited the Rajasthan state in India and, boy, was it a memorable experience. In this post I’d like to share my experiences and hopefully help out somebody that is planning a trip to this funky place.
The reason for which I headed to India in the first place was that my girlfriend was invited to a wedding. Honestly I had no idea of what to expect. After some google-ing I found out that Indian weddings last for days and are a sight to see.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Life - an Interstellar aftermath</title>
      <link>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/interstellar_aftermath/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/interstellar_aftermath/</guid>
      <description>I guess it has been some years now. Unlike many of my peers I believe I have started thinking about “life” from an early age. It was for some long forgotten reason that I realized around the age of 12 that I am going to die one day. Such a terrible thought to think. Especially by a child. Every time it came across my mind there were two outcomes. In one case I just quickly rejected the thought and tossed it aside, continuing my previous work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lighting the torch</title>
      <link>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/lighting_the_torch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/lighting_the_torch/</guid>
      <description>Music is a very powerful tool. It is the universal language that communicates to all people no matter of their race or beliefs. It provokes the mind and soul, and sets the imagination free. From a musician’s perspective, music is also a away to express yourself on a higher level. Depending on the mindset of a certain musician having no rules in music can be the biggest freedom or the hardest constraint.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Because it’s hard</title>
      <link>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/because_hard/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/post/because_hard/</guid>
      <description>Leaving the country that you were born in is difficult. The older you are, the more difficult it gets. I made the decision at a stage of my life when it was in place. High education degree, decent job, nice apartment, plenty of hobbies and social contacts. Most importantly I had the loving family, friends and soul mate that every person needs.
I already had what an average person seeks/wants/gets in the best case.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://alexanderzafirov.github.io/zafirov.me/about/</guid>
      <description>Hello and welcome to my blog. My name is Alex and I am a software engineer. After several years of experience in the IT industry I have already faced some of the main challenges it has to offer. I have been part of big/distributed/multicultural/multilingual teams with skill set that varies from junior to top-notch devs. I would put myself in the middle of that journey, leaning towards the latter part.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>