<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>thoughts on updating mental models ...</title>
    <link>/tags/thoughts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in thoughts on updating mental models ...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/thoughts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Software development</title>
      <link>/posts/software_development/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/software_development/</guid>
      <description>Developers, software engineers, coders. Many names that in all honesty refer to the same persona. But what do these people do all day? Why are they in such high demand? Why do they get such high salaries? Why don&amp;rsquo;t they conform to the norms that people laid out for many years as far as clothing, procedures, communication skills go? I will attempt to answer these and other questions in this post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Dixa is built</title>
      <link>/posts/how_dixa_is_built/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/how_dixa_is_built/</guid>
      <description>Making software in this day and age seems like a trivial task. There are cloud providers - Amazon Web Services (AWS), Google Cloud Platform (GCP), Azure - open-source languages, tools and frameworks, and many sources like blogs/podcasts/youtube channels where experienced engineers share their success and failure. Thus theoretically it should not be hard to get a good idea, write some code and fulfil a need that&amp;rsquo;s out there. I personally agree and disagree with this statement.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Christmas journey through Europe</title>
      <link>/posts/journey_xmas_eu/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/journey_xmas_eu/</guid>
      <description>This year I decided that instead of making my regular 3 hour plane trip towards home for Christmas, I will instead join some friends for a road trip through the old continent. I did that with the clear understanding that it will take 3 days - of which the majority would be spent into the confined space of a car. Yes, it does seem counterintuitive since:
 it doesn&amp;rsquo;t get you from point A to point B that fast and it&amp;rsquo;s holiday season and there are many cars on the highways and the weather conditions can be difficult to drive in etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leaving a trail</title>
      <link>/posts/leaving_trail/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/leaving_trail/</guid>
      <description>When we make decisions about our career we can never be absolutely sure whether they will play out the way we expect them. Having switched my job several times with an average stay at a position of 2 years, I can easily say that job switching has allowed me to be excited about work, meet new people, see different points of view and continuously learn. Along the way I have tried to gather as much knowledge applicable to any domain that I&amp;rsquo;m crafting software for.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modern day office job health tips</title>
      <link>/posts/desk_health/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/desk_health/</guid>
      <description>As a person doing an primarily sitting type of job I am sure you will relate to some of the following health issues:
 eye strain lower back pain wrist pain headaches reduced mobility trouble falling asleep etc.  Depending on which part of the world you live in, office working conditions may or may not be viewed as a contributor to these things. I am lucky to be part of a society where these things matter and people are conscientious about their health.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Staying present</title>
      <link>/posts/present_quick/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/present_quick/</guid>
      <description>If you aren&amp;rsquo;t familiar with the concept of being (in the) present, let me quickly bring you up to speed. We lead our daily lives stormed by visual stimuli. They bombard us at every step from the moment we go out into the real or the digital world. That is slowly starting to wear people down. The reason is that from an evolutionary standpoint the increased amount of visual signals make us more alert and push us in fight-or-flight mode.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goodbye cruel Facebook world</title>
      <link>/posts/no_fb/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/no_fb/</guid>
      <description>Before I write this I want to assure you that this is no plead for attention. For anyone that has been a part of my contacts on the aforementioned social network - you would know that I am mainly reposting articles that I read. So in a sense I use FB as another way to store articles.
The other day I was talking to a friend and he said &amp;ldquo;Man, I&amp;rsquo;m gonna leave this shit one day soon&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2017</title>
      <link>/posts/challenges/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/challenges/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; already! But why is that? To answer that question first let me walk you through my year.
As is obvious I haven&amp;rsquo;t written much in 2017 and that is for a reason. I traveled, I faced obstacles and learned a lot of lessons from my mistakes. If 2016 was a year of changes then 2017 was that and some more so I name the last 12 months - a year of challenges.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2016</title>
      <link>/posts/changes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/changes/</guid>
      <description>2016 was a rough year. Everywhere you look you see turmoil. Brexit, Trump, Syria, Nice, Berlin, Migrants, &amp;hellip; And here comes a question - has this world been in a tougher spot? Of course. An we have always persevered. How? By being human!
I will come back to this thought but first let me take you through my 2016. It was also full of highs and lows. Fortunately for me it peaked in mainly positive outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I against I</title>
      <link>/posts/iagainsti/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/iagainsti/</guid>
      <description>I have enjoyed physical activity from a very early age. Since I was blessed with being a child of the pre-computer era I spent my free time outside on the street, playing with my peers. I clearly remember the endless summer days when I was chasing a football with my legs covered in black and blue spots from all the falls they had to bear. While competing against other players I came to know what it means to win and lose.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trip to Rajasthan, India</title>
      <link>/posts/trip_rajastan/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/trip_rajastan/</guid>
      <description>I recently visited the Rajasthan state in India and, boy, was it a memorable experience. In this post I’d like to share my experiences and hopefully help out somebody that is planning a trip to this funky place.
The reason for which I headed to India in the first place was that my girlfriend was invited to a wedding. Honestly I had no idea of what to expect. After some google-ing I found out that Indian weddings last for days and are a sight to see.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ruminations on life</title>
      <link>/posts/interstellar_aftermath/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/interstellar_aftermath/</guid>
      <description>I guess it has been some years now. Unlike many of my peers I believe I have started thinking about “life” from an early age. It was for some long forgotten reason that I realized around the age of 12 that I am going to die one day. Such a terrible thought to think. Especially by a child. Every time it came across my mind there were two outcomes. In one case I just quickly rejected the thought and tossed it aside, continuing my previous work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lighting the torch</title>
      <link>/posts/lighting_the_torch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/lighting_the_torch/</guid>
      <description>Music is a very powerful tool. It is the universal language that communicates to all people no matter of their race or beliefs. It provokes the mind and soul, and sets the imagination free. From a musician’s perspective, music is also a away to express yourself on a higher level. Depending on the mindset of a certain musician having no rules in music can be the biggest freedom or the hardest constraint.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Because it’s hard</title>
      <link>/posts/because_hard/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/because_hard/</guid>
      <description>Leaving the country that you were born in is difficult. The older you are, the more difficult it gets. I made the decision at a stage of my life when it was in place. High education degree, decent job, nice apartment, plenty of hobbies and social contacts. Most importantly I had the loving family, friends and soul mate that every person needs.
I already had what an average person seeks/wants/gets in the best case.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>